Hello everyone. Today we'll solve the last question of the sheet that we didn't get to solve in large group tutorial.
So starting with the question, we want to do a tail recursive implementation of the function reverse.
So the first thing to do here is to see the default visible reverse function, which is what we can do by doing this.
So here we can see the original one, so you have the defining equations of it.
So it's a reverse of an empty list, then an empty list, then reverse of an empty list is going to be that.
So you take the first element and then you append it to the end of the list, and this is the append.
So the recursive function, if an auto recursive call does not call anything after itself.
So, for instance, the implementation of reversing Isabelle is not a tail recursive because we call reverse on the rest of the list,
and then we call append. So this is the last call, there is a call of something else after itself in the recursive call.
So we want to write an alternative definition. So here we would use reverse tail recursive,
and we want to take a list and return to us a list, and we want that to recursive, take something, and then...
So this is the signature function. So how can it be tail recursive?
So the way tail recursion is done, in general, is by using an accumulator argument.
So in fact, we can define an auxiliary function, which is an actual tail recursive function,
and then TR of TR will be defined in terms of this first function.
So this is, I will just call this auxiliary and then auxiliary, and this takes an accumulator.
So usually when you want to do something as a tail recursive function, you would give it a second argument,
an accumulator, that has the result of the computation until now.
So here I'm just calling this argument ACK, for example, right?
So the function here will define it to be recursive on the first argument,
so the usual template, which is one case for the empty case and one for the non-empty list case.
So for an empty list, all what we do is we execute an accumulator, which is the result of the computation until now.
For an empty list, we call the function recursively, right?
We will change the accumulator so that it has the result of the computation until now, right?
So if we give this function, if we change the accumulator by adding x, for example, like this,
let's test what that would return to us.
So let me see, value, rev, tr auxiliary, and then we give it the empty accumulator.
So this actually doesn't reverse anything, right?
So what we need to do, in fact, is to put this on the front of the list,
and then the next element of x's will be put on the front of that.
So here, if you try to actually run it, you'll see that this is how it reverses,
because you put the first element in the front, and then the one after it before the first,
to the second before the first, and then the third before the second, and so on.
So that reverses the list.
So that is the auxiliary function.
And then, if you want to reverse some given function, all we do is just,
we call reverse the recursive auxiliary with that and the empty accumulator, right?
Okay, so what do we want to show for this function?
We want to show that reverse the recursive x's equals reverse x's, okay?
So let's, first of all, if you have defined the function in terms of another function,
you have to prove whatever you want to prove in terms of the lowest level function.
So here, in this case, it's auxiliary function.
So we have to prove that first, and then prove the lemma of the function
that is defined in terms of reverse the recursive auxiliary.
So as we have always discussed, if you have a function that is recursive in terms of lists,
we can prove that it's something about it by induction on the list,
which is the recursive argument for the function.
So here, we have two cases, right?
So the empty case, so is that here.
So we'll do it with information, but as you can see,
the empty case, you can, of course, do it by just substituting both definitions.
And the step case, so let's see it, which is usually the more interesting case.
Here we have, we want to prove the theorem, but for A appended to x's, right?
And the induction hypothesis is the same theorem, but A appended to x,
but only just for x's, right?
So this is how it looks.
So now, this is induction hypothesis, and this is the goal that we want.
So how can we prove that?
So let me just show the induction hypothesis.
So we have this, and we have that, and we want to rewrite this
so that the induction hypothesis is usable.
So in order for us to rewrite this, we would do the obvious thing.
We would substitute the definition of reverse the recursive auxiliary
and get the A into the accumulator.
So we can do this manually.
So first of all, I'm going to say add this equals xA, right?
Apply substitution, reverse the recursive auxiliary.
Okay, so that's the first thing we prove.
But now, okay, does this match the induction hypothesis?
So look at the induction hypothesis here, and look at what we have.
So for the induction hypothesis, we can only substitute
reverse the recursive auxiliary of x's, which matches the first part
of our current state, of the right-hand side of this new statement I proved.
But it can only apply if the list is empty.
Here we have a list that is not empty.
So this is a typical case of an induction hypothesis that is too weak.
So how can we fix that?
We can fix that by strengthening the induction hypothesis,
or in other words, generalizing the theorem, right?
So instead of saying reverse x's and an empty accumulator,
we'll just say a general accumulator, right?
And that general accumulator would then allow us to substitute
that general accumulator with this singleton list A, right?
But first, the base case broke because, in fact, this doesn't hold as it is, right?
The only way for you to get this to work, actually,
is by saying that it is the same as reverse x's.
We append it to the accumulator that way, and so we append it.
So we put that accumulator in the end of this reverse x's.
But let's see, maybe the statement is wrong,
and we'll discover that part during the proof.
So now the induction hypothesis has an accumulator, right?
And then we can try to substitute to say that this,
to use our induction hypothesis, so we can say
have this thing equals reverse x's
and append it with a singleton list, which is the accumulator, right?
So let us try to substitute the induction hypothesis,
and it doesn't work.
And in fact, it doesn't work because we have a specific accumulator, right?
We are fixing an accumulator.
We need to say for any accumulator, this is the case.
Because remember, when you have a free variable,
like this accumulator, ACC here, outside of the theorem,
this is a universally quantified variable.
But inside of your proof, this is a fixed variable, right?
So now we have a universally quantified variable
outside of the theorem and inside of the theorem.
So now, in fact, it does work because Isabelle is able to say,
okay, I will just match this singleton list A
with that accumulator that is universally quantified.
And as you can see here, we have this question mark.
And now we have that.
So we can use our shorthand notation, which is that.
And say also this equals dot dot that.
Oh, sorry.
I can do it only in the second one.
Okay, let's just, I'm just doing manually first.
Okay, now we have this.
What is our goal?
Our goal is to show that, given a specific accumulator ACC,
which here has the orange color,
the reverse, the reverse auxiliary of A cons Xs
is the same as reverse, the normal reverse of A cons Xs
with, appended to those here, through that cumulative, right?
So let's have that.
So we need to actually change our left-hand side
to talk about the fixed accumulator, the orange accumulator, right?
So here we have that, and then to here we have A cons
that accumulator, right?
That's the definition of reversed, like this TR auxiliary.
Look here again, you can take an X
and then put it at the front of the accumulator.
So that's what I did there, just to define the definition.
And then instead of talking about the singleton list A,
we're talking about a list that has more
than just a singleton list.
So here we have this, and then we append that
to A cons ACC, because, okay, so now we want it,
again, to apply the induction hypothesis,
and what does induction hypothesis say?
The induction hypothesis says, reverse TR auxiliary,
Xs of any accumulator is the same as reverse Xs
and any accumulator, right?
And here I just, we match this,
or either I was able to match this
with this entire list, right?
So now we did that translation.
So remember, the goal of proof by induction
is always to apply the induction hypothesis.
So here the induction hypothesis is an equality,
so we always want to substitute it,
and we always keep trying to substitute it until we can.
So here we were able to substitute it,
and we started from the left-hand side of the goal,
and we're trying to reach the right-hand side.
And then the next step is, okay, we want to take this
and go one more time.
How can we do that?
So what is the right-hand, what is the goal actually?
Now, so let's see the goal.
So the goal is to say that this left-hand side,
which is the beginning, equals reverse that way,
not reverse, of a const x is appended to accumulator.
So we want to basically say that this is equals
to a x's appended with the accumulator, right?
So what kind of theorem can we use there?
So we need the theorem that says
that x's reverse of some list appended to another list,
you can take something from that appended list
and put it into the front of the argument to reverse.
So here we want to take the a, for example,
but we want to take something,
we want to take any,
we probably want something more general than that.
So let's just write the lemma to just explain.
So we want to basically have something like reverse
that says reverse x's appended with some list,
y's equals reverse a with x's appended with y's.
So that's what we want to find.
So let's try and see if there's something like this
in our library.
Okay, there's nothing that is exactly like this.
So we probably need something more general.
So in fact, we can also say that,
so here I'm coming up with these things,
but this usually probably doesn't be used to this,
but you usually would spend some time thinking
about a more general version until you find it,
until you're able to guess the version.
So here, for example, I would say, okay,
if we have a z instead instead of the x's,
let's see if we have this.
Yeah, this also is not there.
So let me see if auto can do it for us.
Yeah, auto can do it.
So there must be something that implies this,
but I don't know what it is.
But you basically would keep...
So there's this hole actually.
So if you have an x's like this,
appended to that.
Yeah, I think we will have to reverse this.
So what is the limit if auto used to prove this?
Oh yeah, so auto probably just...
Now I understand.
Auto can get this actually by just substituting
the definition of reverse, the defining equations of reverse.
So look here, so if we substitute this,
reverse a const x's and do that,
it will give us...
It will put this a in the end, right?
And then, so let's just do that.
That's the first step.
So this is equal to a,
which was rewrite the...
No, sorry, I'm going in reverse here.
So here, I'm going in reverse.
Let me just...
Yeah, so here I want to...
Okay, I'm going in reverse.
So here we have the result of reverse a hash x's
already simplified to the most simple form,
which is the a is completely extracted outside
and then added to the ACC.
So I want to firstly show that this is the same as that.
And this is...
This should follow from the associativity of append
because...
Okay, let's just do this even in a more elementary way.
So we have reverse x's like that.
And then we just say this is...
So what I'm doing here is just showing that a const accumulator
is the same as the singleton list a,
appended accumulator, right?
This is a very simple step.
It should follow from a theorem that talks about
appending a singleton any list.
So it should be...
Yeah, it should...
No, it's not that.
It's not that.
It should follow from the definition of append also.
So substitution append since...
So here we have a const empty list
and appended...
So this appended
with accumulator is the same as
a const the empty list appended with accumulator.
And then we want to say that
okay, the empty list appended with accumulator
is going to be the same as the accumulator.
So if we apply again this substitution,
we have...
So the second substitution is actually...
The second defining equation of append.
So let's just see append simps.
We'll see what we're doing here.
So append simps is...
So for the empty list, appending an empty list
with something is the same as the list.
And appending a list const like x const something
is going to be x const that thing
appended to the other list.
So here, look at how the parentheses are.
Like here, if you want to read this right-hand side,
you should put a left bracket here
and a right bracket here, right?
Okay.
So that's the first step.
And then we want to say...
Okay, I want to restart from the right-hand side here.
From...
And then say...
I want to say that this is the same.
All I'm doing here is just
rearranging the parentheses.
And this is only the associativity of append.
They can look for that, but it's the same
as looking of anything else, okay?
And then lastly, we want to say that
this is...
This is exactly the same as
reverse a on x's.
That just follows from reverse definition.
Or reverse simps, right?
Remember that?
So here we have that definition.
So this is the same as that.
So if we substitute the definition,
second equation definition,
we rewrite this,
and it will match exactly the left-hand side.
And lastly, okay,
so now we have done basically the proof.
So this is the left-hand side
and this is the right-hand side.
So I can just call these theorems
1, 2, 3, etc.
And then substitute all of them in the goal.
Or the right way to do this,
the shorthand way in Isabelle to do this
is to actually tell Isabelle that
this is a chain of equalities that I have been intended.
So you can just say this is equal to that.
And also have...
So here you keep carrying with you the right-hand sides.
Actually, the first one has to be written, of course, fully,
because you have to write every term at least once.
So you write this into that
and then I want to rewrite that again.
So we just write the dots here
and then it knows that we refer to the left-hand side
of the previous equation and so on and so forth.
So this removes all the redundancies that we have.
We have that as well.
And then also have...
So no, so this is actually finally had the goal,
which is just that the left-hand side
is the same as the right-hand side.
So let's say we have that.
It's just a dot because the previous chain of equations,
like Isabelle automatically says,
like contracts all the intermediate steps
and as long as you're adding these equations,
then when you say finally,
it just concludes that you may...
It gives you the theorem that the fact that this
is equal to the left-hand side of the first
equality is the same as the right-hand side
of the last equality.
So that's...
So we have the...
From that, we have this.
And then I can just call this one
and then say using one, we have the case
or we can also just...
Instead of calling this a name,
you can just say then showcase
and then it's the same exactly as saying using one
and see it's the same as using...
Calling this as a name and then using it here.
Okay, so that's the first lemma.
And then now this lemma.
So here I'm going to do, in fact,
an applause script directly at the proof of the theorem.
So I'll just call this reverse,
you know, auxiliary, reverse.
So the recursive is the other one.
And then...
Sorry.
And then you say using this
and then you say by auto,
it doesn't work.
Why is it not working?
So let me just unfold the definition
of inverse PR,
so reverse auxiliary equals access.
And then we have this theorem.
So we just want to instantiate the accumulator
with the empty list.
So I would just say apply,
substitute by that.
And then we have reverse access.
Appended with empty list is the same as reverse access.
And then there is a lemma, I think.
Try to find it.
Appended with the empty list is the same as itself.
So I would just say append nil to what is called.
So here we can say apply,
substitution, append.
And we're done.
So here, first of all,
how can we use auto to do this?
So we need...
We can just...
Okay, I'll just apply and say apply auto
and see what it tells us.
So it actually gave us this.
So we still have to prove that reverse-circuit
is an auxiliary, access, empty is the same as that
because it doesn't know
that we have proved this lemma there.
So we can give this lemma to auto
as a substitution rule,
because we're using it for substitution
in our manual proof.
So we can give this lemma to auto
here, and that finishes the goal.
Why didn't we need to give it
this lemma and that lemma as well?
Well, because those are the two lemmas.
This one is registered with auto
because this is the definition of the function
and definitions of these recursive functions
which are defined using the command fund.
Always registered with auto as simplification rules
or substitution rules.
And this one is added to it in the Isabelle Library.
So we can go there.
Well, actually, this one is not,
but probably another one with the same name is added
to the Isabelle...
to the auto...
to the substitution theorems that auto knows, right?
And then we have just buy auto
and the proof is done.
So that's all.
Thank you for listening.